Speight-McKenney Family papers, Inclusive: 1847-1942, Bulk:1861-1886
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Speight-McKenney Family papers
Inclusive: 1847-1942, Bulk:1861-1886
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
10
McKenney, Florence Speight
8 folders and 1 oversize box
The Speight-McKenney Family papers contains correspondence, calling cards, photographs, poems, songs, and an herbarium. The collection was primarily created by Florence Speight, daughter of prominent early Waco citizen Joseph Speight.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Poor.
Biography/Profile
Florence Josephine Speight McKenney (1847-1922), the first daughter of prominent early Waco citizens Joseph and Josephine S. Pruitt Speight, was born in Mississippi on 1847 September 21. It is unknown what education she received, but she married E.A. McKenney after the Civil War, in 1868. E.A. McKenney was originally from Canada, served as a Captain in the 6th Texas Cavalry during the Civil War, and later became Mayor of Waco after the war. The couple had six children together. Florence McKenny passed away on 1922 December 26, and is buried in Oakwood Cemetery in Waco, Texas.
Scope and Content
The Speight-McKenney Family collection contains a variety of materials, including letters, financial and legal documents, photographs, calling cards, poems and songs, and an herbarium. The financial and legal documents include several Civil War-era documents, including a certificate pledging $20,000 for the Confederate war effort, signed by leading Waco citizens of the time such as S.P. Ross, George Barnard, and E.A. McKenney. Many of the calling cards have been personalized with miniature sketches, though it is not known if this was done by Florence Speight. The herbarium preserves around 100 plant and flower specimens in a scrapbook created by Florence Speight when she was fourteen years old.
Arrangement
The Speight-McKenney Family collection was housed in numbered and titled folders prior to recent processing. Existing folder titles were mostly retained. Various inventories and an early finding aid were done for this collection.
Currently, the collection contains one series: I. Collected Materials.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 10. Acquired 1969-00-00
Related Resources
Related references
Conger, Roger N. “Speight, Joseph Warren.” Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed 2021 June 23.
"Joseph Warren Speight." Waco Masonic Lodge 92. Accessed 2021 June 23.
"Joseph W. Speight, Johns C. West, and the Waco Campus of Baylor University." Warwick H. Jenkins Family. Accessed 2020 November 9.
Ryan, Terri Jo. "Preserved Flowers from 1800s Offer Glimpse into Waco's Past." Waco Tribune Herald. 2010 February 13.
Index Terms
Subjects
Art -- Texas.; Women -- Texas -- Waco.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Financial records.; Photographs.; Poems.; Scrapbooks.
- Collected Materials, 1847-1942; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Unknown.
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains various materials created by Florence Speight McKenney and E.A. McKenney, including financial and legal documents, correspondence, songs and poems, art, photographs, and a herbarium. This series is in poor condition.
  - Correspondence, 1868-1942 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Legal and Financial, 1862-1868 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Songs and Poems (1 of 3), 1864-1886 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Songs and Poems (2 of 3), 1864-1886 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Songs and Poems (3 of 3), 1864-1886 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Art, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Book, Morning Thoughts, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Photographs, circa 1868 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Herbarium, 1861 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 1)